You have to make sure you have a robust change management process and make sure you
test in model environments before you make any
change in a production or live environment.
Even with extensive planning and testing,
there are sometimes unintended consequences.
So you must make sure there is a rollback plan.
A rollback is restoring the system to the state.
It was in before the change was made to
the point where we know it was working properly.
Before we introduce changes into the environment,
we need to make sure we review and test
all the patches and can restore the previous configuration.
Maintaining a separate testing environment can
be a logistical challenge for many organizations
as such.
Many do not have separate production and testing environments
to properly vet all patches and system updates.
In this case,
they may rely on vendor third party testing to certify a
new software released based on a generic set of data.
The rollback plan is important in all environments
but it is absolutely critical in those who are unable to fully test a change.